Justin Mayer

Graduate Student in Materials, UC Santa Barbara engineering.ucsb.edu/jmayer

Education

UC Santa Barbara, Santa Barbara, CA

2019-Present

Graduate Student, Materials Department, University of California, Santa Barbara Advisors: Professor Ram Seshadri and Professor Tresa M. Pollock

Northeastern University, Boston, MA

2014-2018

Bachelor of Science, Degree in Chemical Engineering & Physics; Minor in Mathematics

Research Summary

My research focuses on controlling the microstructure of biphasic intermetallic material systems. I study the influence of strain gradients on the magnetic properties of magnetic nanoprecipitates embedded in a nonmagnetic matrix phase. I characterize these composite materials through SQUID magnetometry, x-ray diffraction, and transmission electron microscopy. Experimental work, such as post processing heat treatments, are often guided by first principle density functional theory calculations that I perform.

Professional Experience

HRL Laboratories, Malibu, CA

Materials Researcher

January 2019–August 2019

- · Applied the grain refinement technology from initial co-op to additional unweldable alloy systems
- · Designed and characterized a novel solid-state device for sourcing and sinking alkali vapor
- Developed Matlab scripts to analyze x-ray computed tomography measurements of a ceramic composite
 Undergraduate Co-op
 May 2016–December 2016
- · Performed electroless Ni-P plating for thermal barrier coating of piston crowns
- · Studied the potential to refine grain structure of 3D printed aluminum alloys
- · Filed invention disclosure on a novel precursor material to be used in future welding processes

Dipartimento di Fisica, Universitá degli Studi di Milano, Milan, Italy

Research Assistant

July 2017–December 2017

- · Prepared gold nanoparticles embedded in amorphous silicon through DC magnetron sputtering
- · Characterized amorphous silicon grown on gold nanoparticles via X-ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy

Mefford Magnetic & Nanostructured Materials Research Group, Clemson, SC

Research Assistant

May 2015–July 2015

- · Studied the binding properties of different polymer end groups to the surface of nanoparticles
- · Quantified ligand exchange activity of iron oxide nanoparticles with liquid scintillation counting

Teaching

Northeastern University

Physics I and Physics II Peer Tutor; Founder of Physics II peer tutoring program

Undergraduate teaching assistant for Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics I

Publications

- C. Lenardi, J. Mayer, G. Faraone, J. Cardoso, S. Marom, R. Modi, A. Podestá, S. Kadkho-dazadeh, and M. Di Vece, Nanoscale induced formation of silicide around gold nanoparticles encapsulated in a-Si, *Langmuir* 36 (2020) 939–947. [doi]
- J. Cardoso, S. Marom, J. Mayer, R. Modi, A. Podestá, X. Xie, M. A. van Huis, and M. Di Vece, Germanium Quantum Dot Grätzel-Type Solar Cell, *Phys. Status Solidi A*, 215 (2018) 1800570.
 [doi]
- 4. J. H. Martin, B. D. Yahata, E. C. Clough, **J. A. Mayer**, J. M. Hundley, and T. A. Schaedler, Additive manufacturing of metal matrix composites via nanofunctionalization, *MRS Commun.* 8 (2018) 297–302.[doi]
- 3. K. Davis, M. Vidmar, A. Khasanov, B. Cole, M. Ghelardini, **J. Mayer**, C. Kitchens, A. Nath, B. Powell, and O. T. Mefford, The effect of post-synthesis aging on ligand exchange activity of iron oxide nanoparticles, *J. Colloid Interface Sci.* **511** (2018) 374–382. [doi]
- 2. J. H. Martin, B. D. Yahata, E. C. Clough, R. D. Mone, **J. A. Mayer**, E. Stonkevitch, R. C. Schubert, J. A. Miller, J. M. Hundley, T. A. Schaedler, and T. M. Pollock, Recent advances in additive manufacturing of high strength 7000 series aluminum, *Adv. Mater. Processes* **176** (2018) 18–22. [doi]
- 1. J. H. Martin, B. D. Yahata, J. M. Hundley, J. A. Mayer, T. A. Schaedler, and T. M. Pollock, 3D printing of high-strength aluminium alloys, *Nature* **549** (2017) 365–369. [doi]

Patents

U.S. Application No. 15/880,452, Nanoparticle composite welding filler materials, and methods for producing the same; B. Yahata, *J. Mayer*, and J. H. Martin. Filed February 2017. Patent Pending.

Presentations

National:

J. Mayer, S. Cranford, (2015, August). Computationally optimizing fullerenols as specific non-covalent drug carriers: discriminating H-bond anchoring, van der Waals adhesion and electrostatic interactions. Oral presentation at the American Chemical Society conference, Boston, MA.

Regional:

- **J. Mayer**, E. Levin, Y. Eggeler, L. Kautzsch, K. Gates, D. Gianola, T. M. Pollock, and R Seshadri, (2020, January) Engineering interfacial strain gradients in biphasic half-Heusler composites. Poster presentation at Materials Research Outreach Program, Santa Barbara, CA.
- **J. Mayer**, B. Yahata, J. H. Marting, (2016, December). Implementation of grain refiners within additively manufactured high strength aluminum alloys. Oral presentation at HRL Laboratories, Malibu, CA.
- **J. Mayer**, K. Davis, O. T. Mefford, (2015, June), The effect of aging surfaces on ligand exchange. Poster presentation at Clemson University's interfaces and surfaces research experience for undergraduates, Clemson University, Clemson, SC.

Please see engineering.ucsb.edu/jmayer for the latest version of this document, including updated publications. A list of manuscripts in preparation is available upon request.